<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Alex Leeds</title>
<link>https://alexleeds.com/reading/</link>
<atom:link href="https://alexleeds.com/reading/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Alex Leeds is a data scientist living in NYC</description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.537</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 May 2024 04:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Table for Two by Amor Towles</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Leeds</dc:creator>
  <link>https://alexleeds.com/reading/table_for_two/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><strong>Rating:</strong> 90/100</p>
<p><strong>Comments</strong></p>
<p>Amor Towles is best known for <em>A Gentleman in Moscow</em>, the fictional account of a Russian aristocrat imprisoned in a high-end hotel by the Bolsheviks. <em>A Gentleman in Moscow</em> has a fast pace, sharp dialogue and terrific humor, and it is no surprise that it appears on many “Best Books of XYZ” lists.</p>
<p>By comparison, I found the short stories in <em>Table for Two</em> more polarizing. Some (“Hasta Luego”, “The Bootlegger”, “Eve in Hollywood”) were excellent. Others (“The Line”, “The Ballad of Timothy Touchett”, and “I Will Survive”) were disappointing.</p>
<p>Towles’s best characters - such as Count Rostov in <em>A Gentleman in Moscow</em> and Eve in a <em>Table for Two</em> - are flawless. Like the heroes of your favorite action flick, they overcome every obstacle with flair. Eve is so far ahead of everyone around her that she outwits them, charms them, and astonishes adversaries by appearing exactly where she needs to be. Towles makes Eve perfectly attractive as well. Her only imperfection as a noticeable scar on her face as though to qualify this absurdity.</p>
<p>Towles doesn’t always bend to the standard that characters must suffer in “good” fiction. Flawless characters are fun. And Eve’s combination of kindness, omniscience, and dominance is even better in print than it would be on the screen, capering for 200 pages in <em>Table for Two</em> across 1930s Los Angeles.</p>
<p>This makes some of his other stories so much less appealing. In “The Ballad of Timothy Touchett,” Towles expresses an oozing disdain for inept writers. The same disdain appears in different guises for the characters in “The Line” (about a passive, good-natured Russian farmer) and “I Will Survive” (about an interfering Upper East Side daughter). And when he writes about people whose failings lead to tragic ends, he can’t hide his enthusiasm for punishing human weaknesses. Some people might like it, but I find this artless.</p>
<p>Towles is better off when his characters have sympathetic flaws (“Hasta Luego” and “The Bootlegger”). In both of these stories, the protagonists are married to spouses who love them anyway. And, as though depicting that love makes him more tolerant, Towles produces more moving stories.</p>
<p><em>Table for Two</em> is easy to recommend. Every story was entertaining. And “Eve in Hollywood” was both the best and the full second half of the book. The familiar scenes from Central Park to Brooklyn to LaGuardia Airport were fun to have so well-captured by a local author, and sun-bleached LA was equally vibrant.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>fiction</category>
  <category>new york city</category>
  <guid>https://alexleeds.com/reading/table_for_two/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://alexleeds.com/reading/table_for_two/table_for_two.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Leviathan Wakes by James S. A. Corey</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Leeds</dc:creator>
  <link>https://alexleeds.com/reading/leviathan_wakes/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><strong>Rating:</strong> 80/100</p>
<p><strong>Comments</strong></p>
<p>I’ll keep this vague to avoid spoilers:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Leviathan-Wakes-James-S-Corey/dp/0316129089">Leviathan Wakes</a> was recommended by Dario Amodei, the CEO of Anthropic, in his <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/04/12/opinion/ezra-klein-podcast-dario-amodei.html">April 12, 2024 interview</a> with Ezra Klein.</p></li>
<li><p>It’s no surprise that the novel was basis for an Amazon Prime TV series (which I haven’t seen). It has propulsive storytelling and space opera visuals of the sort that would translate to the screen.</p></li>
<li><p>The plot follows the usual “small to grand scale” arc as its main characters get swept up in transformational events across the future inhabited solar system.</p></li>
<li><p>Like so much good sci-fi, the main characters (Holden leading his ice-hauling crew and Miller, the cop) were heroically “good”: persistant, brave, kind, and fair as well as humorously rebellious. They’re the usual <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Hero_with_a_Thousand_Faces">hero with a thousand faces</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>The creepy things were extremely creepy. A+ for goulishness.</p></li>
<li><p>I liked the fact that the characters were casually clever. Miller’s brilliance is never presented as a central part of his personality. In fact, he just refers to himself as someone who had once been an effective cop. Yet, his creative problem solving is a thread that runs through the story.</p></li>
<li><p>This book does not deviate from the typical male-centered view of sci-fi. The two main female characters were romantic interests of the two main male characters.</p></li>
<li><p>There is an assumption that everyone in the story makes about the aim of the “protomolecule” that seemed like a strange leap to me.</p></li>
<li><p>I loved the surprises. There was one twist you will see coming from hundreds of pages away (but still enjoy) but lots that kept me glued.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>Overall, this is a good beach read. I probably <em>will</em> read more of the series on the beach this summer.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>science fiction</category>
  <category>fantasy</category>
  <guid>https://alexleeds.com/reading/leviathan_wakes/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://alexleeds.com/reading/leviathan_wakes/leviathan_wakes_wikipedia.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
