<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Alex Leeds</title>
<link>https://alexleeds.com/reading/</link>
<atom:link href="https://alexleeds.com/reading/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Alex Leeds is a data scientist living in NYC</description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.537</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 04:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Notes on Leviathan Wakes</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Leeds</dc:creator>
  <link>https://alexleeds.com/reading/leviathan_wakes/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><strong>Rating:</strong> 80/100</p>
<p><strong>Comments</strong></p>
<p>I’ll keep this vague to avoid spoilers:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>This book was recommended by Dario Amodei, the CEO of Anthropic, in his <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/04/12/opinion/ezra-klein-podcast-dario-amodei.html">April 12, 2024 interview</a> with Ezra Klein.</p></li>
<li><p>It’s no surprise that the novel became the basis for a Syfy and Amazon Prime Video series (which I haven’t seen). It has propulsive storytelling and space opera visuals of the sort that would translate to the screen.</p></li>
<li><p>The plot follows the usual “small to grand scale” arc as its main characters get swept up in transformational events across the future inhabited solar system.</p></li>
<li><p>Like so much good sci-fi, the main characters (Holden leading his ice-hauling crew and Miller, the cop) were heroically “good”: persistant, brave, kind, and fair as well as humorously rebellious. They’re the usual <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Hero_with_a_Thousand_Faces">hero with a thousand faces</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>The creepy things were extremely creepy. A+ for goulishness.</p></li>
<li><p>I liked the fact that the characters were casually clever. Miller’s brilliance is never presented as a central part of his personality. In fact, he just refers to himself as someone who had once been an effective cop. Yet, his creative problem solving is a thread that runs through the story.</p></li>
<li><p>This book does not deviate from male-centered tropes of sci-fi. The two main female characters were love interests of the two main male characters and all of the significant leadership were men. The women do at least play pivotal roles.</p></li>
<li><p>There is an assumption that everyone in the story makes about the aim of the “protomolecule” that seemed like a strange leap to me.</p></li>
<li><p>I loved the surprises. There was one twist you will see coming from hundreds of pages away (but still enjoy) but lots that kept me glued.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>Overall, this is a good beach read. I probably <em>will</em> read more of the series on the beach this summer.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>science fiction</category>
  <category>fantasy</category>
  <guid>https://alexleeds.com/reading/leviathan_wakes/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://alexleeds.com/reading/leviathan_wakes/leviathan_wakes_wikipedia.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
