<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Alex Leeds</title>
<link>https://alexleeds.com/writing/</link>
<atom:link href="https://alexleeds.com/writing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Alex Leeds is a data scientist living in NYC</description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.537</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 04:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Organizational Growth as a Navigation Problem</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Leeds</dc:creator>
  <link>https://alexleeds.com/writing/org-growth/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Two angles for thinking about organizational growth are <em>navigation</em> and <em>competition</em>. Navigation refers to how an organization steers through its environment toward promising opportunities. Competition more focused on the methods an organization uses to fight.</p>
<p>Competitive strategy might determine where an organization “goes” in the long term. But I think navigation is an essential focus for fast growing organizations, and not as common as classic strategic analysis (five forces, flywheels, zero-to-one, etc).</p>
<p>When your product is better than the competition, you can get huge growth by exploiting your advantages to the hilt: growing into <em>open</em> territory. To do that, navigating requires a clear picture of the landscape, not competitive calculations. If you could only see the opportunity, then you would simply go there. And the difference of a few degrees in direction might be the difference between hitting a vein of gold or missing it completely. Or, more modestly, the benefit of shifting your worst 30% of ads to the performance of your best 30%.</p>
<p>We can think of organizational navigation as the challenge of a self-driving car: First, it needs to see and recognize the features of the environment. Therefore…</p>
<section id="navigating-in-2024" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="navigating-in-2024">Navigating in 2024</h2>
<p>To navigate places, you have to have good sensors.</p>
<p>For growth strategy, your sensors are measures of what potential customers want, what they learn or know about you (and respond to emotionally), and “where” they exist online and off. Most companies have strong intuitions about these but they don’t always measure them well.</p>
<p>The techniques are pretty straightforward. They include:</p>
<p><img src="https://alexleeds.com/writing/org-growth/methods_of_seeing.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>These techniques (very) roughly use these data inputs:</p>
<p><img src="https://alexleeds.com/writing/org-growth/methods_of_seeing_labeled.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>To excel with at these techniques, there are three steps that take a concerted effort.</p>
<p><strong>(1) Gather this data on a regular cadence.</strong></p>
<p>Certain “slow” measurements (e.g.&nbsp;interviews) might happen twice a year. Certain fast measurements might happen every hour. But it is important to have predictability in these feedback loops so that people embed the information in their operations. These need to be really smooth: when people need the analysis, it should be at their fingertips, if not automating organizational tactics directly.</p>
<p><strong>(2) Capture the same data about your target markets and your existing customers</strong></p>
<p>With data about your target markets and your existing customers, you get obvious charts that look like this:</p>
<p><img src="https://alexleeds.com/writing/org-growth/market_map1.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The same chart can be produced for <strong>verticals</strong> <em>or</em> <strong>interest in product features</strong> <em>or</em> <strong>geographic regions</strong> <em>or</em> <strong>media audience</strong> and it can be modified to reflect cost to acquire a customer instead of scale.</p>
<p>A slight variation of this chart can show the % of highly likely customers in a vertical vs.&nbsp;the % of customers in that vertical who know about you.</p>
<p><strong>(3) Study the same dynamics across interviews, surveys, and quantitative data sets.</strong></p>
<p>It is classically true that interviews explain “why” someone might want or love your product but when, where, why, or how. That said, there are lots of established techniques for bridging interviews, surveys, and product data – but it requires planned coordination.</p>
<p>The payoff, of course, is that once you know what types of messaging consumers respond to (interviews), you can test those in your marketing material (experiments), and validate the impact on LTV (product data), and create feedback between techniques.</p>
<p><strong>(4) Your navigation must support your means of locomotion.</strong></p>
<p>The goal isn’t to change organizational behavior, it is to supercharge it.</p>
<p>Sticking with the “seeing where to go” analogy, we can consider the market’s response to two devices that want to change how people see things: the Facebook Quest VR headset and the Apple Vision Pro.</p>
<p>A strong signal that the Apple Vision Pro is succeeding is that people say they love using it for two specific activities: watching movies and reading email.</p>
<p>Facebook burnt billions of dollars trying to get people to do new things with Quest headsets, exploring their metaverse or playing brand new games. Meanwhile, Apple seems to have triumphed by producing a device that improves everyday lives. If everyday Americans will dump money on a home theater system, it isn’t such a stretch for them to buy the Vision Pro to make the same experience better.</p>
<p>Once people adopt the Apple Vision Pro for movies, or sports watching, or email, then the gateway opens to create new experiences. The same is true for growth feedback.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@misc{leeds2024,
  author = {Alex Leeds},
  title = {Organizational {Growth} as a {Navigation} {Problem}},
  date = {2024-05-02},
  url = {https://alexleeds.com/writing/org-growth},
  langid = {en-GB}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-leeds2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Alex Leeds. 2024. <span>“Organizational Growth as a Navigation
Problem.”</span> <a href="https://alexleeds.com/writing/org-growth">https://alexleeds.com/writing/org-growth</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>organizational growth</category>
  <category>ad tactics</category>
  <guid>https://alexleeds.com/writing/org-growth/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://alexleeds.com/writing/org-growth/market_map1b.svg" medium="image" type="image/svg+xml"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Magical Skills</title>
  <dc:creator>Alex Leeds</dc:creator>
  <link>https://alexleeds.com/writing/magical-skills/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Barbara Corcoran of the Corcoran (real estate) Group <a href="https://twitter.com/BarbaraCorcoran/status/953716121470939137">recently tweeted</a>, “The hardest lesson to learn is that you are more capable than you think you are.”</p>
<p>I’ve often wondered about this: how do we hem ourselves in by our own expectations?</p>
<p>At a simplistic level, tons of research on <a href="https://faculty.wcas.northwestern.edu/eli-finkel/documents/InPress_BurnetteOBoyleVanEppsPollackFinkel_PsychBull.pdf">implicit beliefs</a>, <a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/manuscript/2020-99903-019.pdf">growth mindset</a>, and <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Martha-Carr-2/publication/38138977_Motivational_Components_of_Underachievement/links/54d3a5a10cf2b0c6146de654/Motivational-Components-of-Underachievement.pdf">underachievement</a> explores the basic idea: If we believe we can’t learn or do something - or just that our skills in some domain are inherited rather than acquired - then we don’t learn it.</p>
<p>But I’m interested in another layer of this problem: opportunities we miss because <em>almost no one</em> believes that a skill is possible for any individual or group. What about the limits we impose from lack of imagination rather than from lack of self-confidence?</p>
<section id="what-impossible-skills-are-actually-possible" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-impossible-skills-are-actually-possible">What “impossible” skills are actually possible?</h2>
<p>What if we lived in a world where long distance running had never been invented as a sport? Would we believe that a human could run 26 miles in under 4:36 seconds per mile? Probably not.</p>
<p>What if we lived in a world where professional musicians didn’t exist, and then imported Yuja Wang? Her performance would seem like magic: the memory of those hundreds of thousands of notes delivered with impossible control.</p>
<p>But there are abilities that most people would probably not imagine at all.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>We can hold our breath for more than 20 minutes (<a href="https://www.wired.com/story/what-it-takes-to-hold-your-breath-for-24-minutes-yeah-its-a-thing/">Wired article</a> and <a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/the-limits-of-breath-holding/">Scientific American</a>).</p></li>
<li><p>We can <a href="https://www.worldmemorychampionships.com/spoken-numbers/">perfectly recall 500 single-digit numbers</a> having heard them listed only once.</p></li>
<li><p>Apollo Robbins can remove your watch <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Zkx-XzEkoHs">without your awareness</a> <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2013/01/07/a-pickpockets-tale">even when you are trying to prevent him</a>.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>The most extreme examples <em>are</em> due to rare talent as well as extreme effort. But a fraction of thesse performances is achievable with concerted long-term effort yet just not “believable” by almost anyone.</p>
<p>Could we do the same with slightly more practical skills? Paul Ekman made a science out of reading people’s emotions (<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Emotions-Revealed-Second-Recognizing-Communication/dp/0805083391">Emotions Revealed</a>), for example. What could we do if we imagined other useful skills?</p>
<p>Imagine if we collected thousands of video clips from YouTube of just people…</p>
<ul>
<li>introducing themselves</li>
<li>making persuasive arguments</li>
<li>interrupting other people</li>
<li>defending a belief</li>
<li>making jokes classified by style</li>
</ul>
<p>How are these done well? When do they fail? This is now a feasible AI project.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-could-groups-do" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-could-groups-do">What could groups do?</h2>
<p>And what about groups? Most of our models for how people behave in social and work settings are based on limited scenarios and narrow comfort levels.</p>
<p>What if we took the hours, focus, and energy of a five-star restaurant kitchen staff and expected Facebook software developers to perform similarly? I think some of them might actually die from exhaustion before the week was over.</p>
<p>Could we change how people think about working as a team in professional settings? What if we really did cross software development with the skills/practical elements of other fields like restaurants, or sports, or concert music? What if we also tailored the workflows of different teams to more accurately reflect the kinds of outcomes t hey aim to produce?</p>
<p>Jensen Huang <a href="https://www.acquired.fm/episodes/jensen-huang">recently made this argument</a>. He criticized engineering firms for adopting a generic pattern for organizational structure and functions. Similarly, I still see hospitals fighting (and failing) to overcome the departmental structure that has existed for decades. And many private equity firms still use approaches that Siegmund Warburg designed in the 1940s and 1950s.</p>
<p>Our expectations for ourselves, for our professions, and for our societies are hide-bound. I’m not sure what to do about it, but I’m certain that we set our sights far too low.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@misc{leeds2024,
  author = {Alex Leeds},
  title = {Magical {Skills}},
  date = {2024-04-13},
  url = {https://alexleeds.com/writing/magical-skills},
  langid = {en-GB}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-leeds2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Alex Leeds. 2024. <span>“Magical Skills.”</span> <a href="https://alexleeds.com/writing/magical-skills">https://alexleeds.com/writing/magical-skills</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>skill acquistion</category>
  <category>team performance</category>
  <guid>https://alexleeds.com/writing/magical-skills/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://alexleeds.com/writing/magical-skills/pina_film.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
